<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-29T20:29:14+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Debashish Reang</title><subtitle>Musings of a Computer Vision and Natural Language Processing enthusiast.</subtitle><author><name>Debashish Reang</name></author><entry><title type="html">Travelogue - New Delhi &amp;amp; Uttarakhand</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/08/delhidoon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travelogue - New Delhi &amp; Uttarakhand" /><published>2019-10-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/08/delhidoon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/08/delhidoon/">&lt;p&gt;I recently went on my first ever solo trip, which included the first-ever train and overnight bus journey. I thought a few people would be curious about the trip, or at least I’ll get to show a few good photos that I shot. :wink:
The original plan was to write it along the way. But, many things came my way, and I couldn’t find the time to write it. The midterm recess has just begun, and so I thought now might be the best time to write it before my memory of the trip starts to fade.  I’ve tried to organize things chronologically, but the truth can be whatever I wish to. :stuck_out_tongue_closed_eyes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to see new places. I also keep a &lt;a href=&quot;/bucket&quot;&gt;bucket list&lt;/a&gt;, and traveling is a big part of it. So, I thought to myself, why not start now. The summer term had just ended, and I had nothing to do except watching movies or wondering about stupid things and getting depressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;where&quot;&gt;Where?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original plan was to travel to New Delhi and stay there for a week. However, a good soul from Delhi suggested that there isn’t much in New Delhi to spend a week there (&lt;strong&gt;which is true!&lt;/strong&gt;). So, I changed plans on the way and ended up going to Dehradun and Mussoorie. From my personal experience I’d say that the change of plans worked out perfectly well. I fell in love with Mussoorie. I’ll list the places I went to (at least what I remember):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kanpur Central&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;India Gate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nehru Park&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lotus Temple&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Qutab Minar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Walls of Red Fort (it was closed. :cry:)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delhi Metro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Streets of New Delhi (I love walking the streets!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humayun’s Tomb&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buddhist Monastery in Clement Town&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pacific Mall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mussoorie&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kempty Falls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kanpur-central-to-new-delhi&quot;&gt;Kanpur Central to New Delhi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never travelled by train (&lt;em&gt;read: I’ve never been inside a train compartment&lt;/em&gt;) and had no idea how the system works. Huge shout out to Luvneesh for walking me through everything patiently. He helped me with finding cheap tickets and how things work. He even went to the extent of instructing how to board the train and what to expect once you board the train and stuff. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/W3aERWZXTeRvI5IajgfDwhKSQV38Kx2EmBsjJXq6hOyxgHd67kvzqRjxwWww0gdfC6RHhCitr91gn2dTL4DWU6mTNoIbJ5w67pRC7fgXSE2GbBF5AFymA_5XtPSbn3TxG9_3ou5nbg=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/sWCEPHhKmhT_GWu864g9uZwcy1cnidHIlBbIgV7wtPBTxcw5IONYfvYykZXFkSekT4Xb1sx4-oJKJejYRZ2ELUIkNsxfk5O1bqm-GDtoLiVkRgLJ9URqWY05PYK3Q4vDtP28gWnTwQ=w2400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-delhi&quot;&gt;New Delhi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached New Delhi on time. My friends Jalpana and Rakesh were kind enough to let me stay at their place. They even came to pick me up from NDLS train station. The solo trip ended up being not so solo when they joined me on my way to Mussoorie. We spent the next few days together. Thanks for everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They showed me around the city and we went to India Gate and Nehru Park which is about 8 km from India Gate. India Gate always reminds me of the time I got a mark less than the full marks in one GK exam because I incorrectly wrote “Gateway of India” instead of “India Gate”. In my defense, “India Gate” sounds so wrong grammatically while “Gateway of India” sounded perfect in every sense. :dancer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Rmw1YkVl-iMaXnDQcsRFeJWcnZ7IsdIhXPPUgR00J0Tn7IO3EXmx4X-Ap-g5RvmHQ8UqkQrxFa-YA-rSpLOlIeuUSiXF8ncmzF21Wca0rkAMaM5qutxy20OLLBeHibRLtxZbtdtq_g=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/m4G1mHQwwlR6A7Z-bUDoDCCdbaZyx6I_FNkxjw3cRwYOF1wav29vEqwne9k5UKgCRB-h01w3siOgIc8X_ubB-dPWmIJBXTMhN2hklGAee0RUK9VgSpSz9K70gHU33q7QqgtFVY07RQ=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/XZ3_eziqmJ6U2KfbROH3dqliwIot-X-01qvEXUT_QNG3U42sh5DyZhy78xPt0QuSU7JmL--HupIUotAV_CqNv7xbKT4y0BjgtILPL0uA1SzqpJRGK8mszHsmCu2O02G3UNaAnxr1gg=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Y04k0uC-MTaHcOeULKfS6D_1YyR7xYcEmC6_dxONkk4KYM-SwKWkeWZLM0dRzwRRKc2RwT7rCg6W-S4j442Jos74CpMY4Ft9SomxKtFSMuDJM_a7O9Tu00qWY1bEXGPBpqtNKsjWew=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/AWc37-pP5k2E8aT9l0_zw-VLKVMYwR0b02y9VBPgCnmq6PT5T6ZMZ5zXoJ2obHOiWXRsjIS7EG4Vg4lR6arHpsy7fdpdxV2ThHuMm9W0ZkfkESXfBJYRVNRF3WxRcTHgUz0PL2oX1Q=w2400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-delhi-to-uttarakhand&quot;&gt;New Delhi to Uttarakhand&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided on the same day that we’ll be traveling to Dehradun. I don’t know what I did but I managed to convince them somehow and hence began the first ever overnight bus journey. They were surprised by my ethusiasm (&lt;em&gt;IITK folks read: &lt;strong&gt;enthu&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s not legal for you all to read otherwise&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/yZFlZSPQ9-u4IiijqjdqEaVz4wHAsIOIipl2vxkFQRRKjsgCUq0bF1uFOrDpUoxhOxE-Yh3YwlfN2Pq8SBRl8iKmMvh4xFy1PZeTq4xcZpbLbzhH4AQvWr4D4ZUXKKJm7_1PY4KNAw=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/eOSr-9m-zyDDDoJU_Lpht4k30P4O62-wVIgvYq6Th1D2s6doeLA47X_eaNs6POYGUf3JIurqtd1YyEoeK_dsjRaGVzaH_BLdc-GFpn8fO8yKabzeMY5t_yN4fw5WtL0NgZioBq4XCw=w2400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spotted a few rabbits in Muzaffarnagar on the way to Dehradun. It was supercool to see them early in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uttarakhand&quot;&gt;Uttarakhand&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While at Uttarakhand, I went to visit a Tibetan Monastery that had great food, among other things. I also met my friends here, after a very long time. They were kind enough to let me stay at their place. Trip to Pacific Mall was great too. Oh, the butter naans in Uttarakhand are way better than the ones in UP. 
Sadly, I did not walk the streets here since my friends were unwilling, and I did not know much about the place, and as far as I remember, it was a sunny day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/n_g1NLsJ6PeUshuYzTnYUJWruW6VWTxMcJB8R8R-3wtUejX51XOzfHnKXLJqMGAXWl4TAbvG0VUvQFLNNOjSvxro8x7P5GJPDy-XQJVIhynvNrQmDbmKkdtG7O4a2dnHwN42anzagQ=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/mOBEQGQEM-ebavTbqgyFX6p94P3Ic_Edl5HDS7pXlyOmvvYnulgasIyKcL43KLZVHRVtDWLlS5TbqZaHPa8ZPB5hDv9iukBvrxS6Zlx2Ymwwoshcov6MyXBUQfeS6Wb_LQ-4wUqxSA=w2400&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day we went to Mussoorie. The weather there was lovely. I spotted a few JCBs along the way (&lt;em&gt;memes, people&lt;/em&gt;). To be honest, I probably could stay there for months without ever getting bored if it was not for the internet connection. They made me dress up in this beautiful dress. Wall climbing always seemed easy to me, but when I tried it myself that day it was a disaster. But, it was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/4M9jNPBqnWgVEhP8Hw05QWURGnDrpl261PEp-DCXEdG_U-z9qnERomNTxERriIAGiyPzRdVwuGd0DsuWRoTpgEfp1JH26OzjMx5KADqj27Xuep0Y1N6Uq7STCn14xUD8DolP8MKv-A=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/wmOz5LFugBWA7QiPbmDRojwjvRxLrxakaBJOeC7cS6DxMZKyCEIrPnqcgkAi3sT5EofKsgUuT6C23umIWjtmjMN0TiHVbD15e9HC5G9pSsCfGGI-pIepntxT1fRrc7sg6tiJzJU1tA=w2400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/cQwqAa8ujUfLwiUrw3-nCiEIFUKXFGjA4Cr49__cnKQ4_YLotckNoiWlBdW77bgwnA7x0jrACPD_rxNOVE8hZjNlUFLTxIn_v790jOIDjKwwhPm5w51ttbW1Q88EEPpFg8JIS4goHw=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/iPS8-gIjgj-FtaVGuYK2L8Gkonc6oAoRHeOL8qScB9w5Tw-B81yNfFeG-qUoiXOd_5Dqs4Sy0oEbnZFQS7C0cMXUyaQfVwFNLtXMwPw6UKjLyNJrZDVKZ9qWsQGkPnCcvUMuNigkyQ=w2400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-new-delhi&quot;&gt;Back to New Delhi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can call this the second leg if you will. I went back to Delhi and spent two more days there. I met a school friend and my coaching teacher aka BMS. They showed me around the city, and the Delhi Metro. Oh, BMS also got me the metro card, which was pretty cool. We went around Connaught place, the food there was delicious. I don’t know about you, but walking to Humayun’s tomb where you can see couples left and right can be pretty overwhelming xD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cards&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/OTrBbBH1tsyAtS-ZBb7isQm9Ru5I4APbQjxDWCkDvbHyXaHhyRrw8cl4rqQYSC5GFZEIKY7IOKcIwtJW6LKAQY_uRAsLVCmrUvVb6zDl1zHSng7VvKxJ2G_LUYtung5scjkHSRmScg=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/YZglwpxrlzG8wXHrM4cbk8tXL6AnLia5rEOpU7Gz-JL-CfsMl5njvBONDG37hlXbrR1vHP5U-Dh161BNH8gK0TB4rh7zfugfXQVgySXjNtK7W9-QiUkgPOhLFV3oary6VlFeonDnvA=w2400&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/N5DJDME5YwzRMrPzW3H60CvzQ3ZXWWsD6l8X6CeKL5OukUk0hZmHR6QJAG8fygnmhc510Vn_kTT4XaVGt5cujUBU4ew7i4j0oaXqmSar-lCXHkbz8-rDsGffp8OQkJyEt92cxAaoRw=w2400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t really know. But, thank you to everyone who helped me on this trip. I guess this experience will help in future trips. I plan on ticking off all the things on my &lt;a href=&quot;/bucket&quot;&gt;bucket list&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;with a few exceptions :cry:&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inspired by&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taniarascia.com/europe/&quot;&gt;Tania Rascia’s&lt;/a&gt; Whirlwind Tour of Europe.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Debashish Reang</name></author><summary type="html">Adventures in the capital and a few words on how I ended up in the lap of the mighty Himalayas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/08/28/welcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome" /><published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/08/28/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/08/28/welcome/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hey! Thanks for stopping by.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a welcome post after two posts is rather hilarious and non-sensical. I want to answer three questions that you might have at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s this blog about?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why should you read the posts at all?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most importantly:&lt;/strong&gt; Why did I start writing in the first place?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if my words would totally convince you. But, I shall make an attempt nonetheless. I envision this blog to be mostly about machine learning: neural nets, relevant calculus, the algorithms that I came across etc. with a few comments on topics of general interest viz. how to do well in something, why something is broken if it’s broken etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you get something out of my writings. Though most of the writing is meant for myself (sort of an online journal, &lt;em&gt;if you will&lt;/em&gt;) if you get something out of it I would be really happy. As a learner I often find myself spending hours trying to understand a new concept or solve a really interesting problem, which seemed trivial to the Professor (so that he/she skips the concept saying it can be easily shown, proved etc.). These writings are sort of my version of the same concept or my proposed solution(s) to the problem. You can think of them as being the sort of explanation that I’d give if I were to teach the same to someone else. I had/shall tried/try my best to keep the explanations simple and accurate. However, the probability of typographical errors or conceptual misunderstaning is high and hence &lt;red&gt;&lt;b&gt;you have been warned&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/red&gt;! Please point out errors if you find any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also working on a series titled &lt;strong&gt;“How I fail”&lt;/strong&gt; that will describe other people’s hard times, and how they overcame it. More details coming soon. So, &lt;strong&gt;stay tuned!&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S01E01&lt;/strong&gt; coming soon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;x&lt;br /&gt;
Reang.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Debashish Reang</name></author><summary type="html">The whys, hows etc. about the blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aakansha: The story of a dreamer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/08/04/aakansha/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aakansha: The story of a dreamer" /><published>2019-08-04T05:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-08-04T05:30:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/08/04/aakansha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/08/04/aakansha/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wrote this mini-article as a part of an assignment assigned by Ms. Rita Singh during the summer. Truth be told, it is really hard to write about someone else. But, I did try nonetheless. This assignment involved interviewing the person, and narrating events that I wasn’t a part of in any way. I hope I did justice to the work assigned. The article may contain grammatical, and other unintended errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aakansha.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aakansha and her mother.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Aakansha (right) and her mother.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was up before the others, before the birds, before the sun. I drank a cup of coffee, wolfed down that last piece of bread, set up my laptop, and sat down to write. I hope I can do justice to the story I am about to write. &lt;strong&gt;This is the story of Aakansha.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider myself fortunate enough for being fortunate enough to hear a story as inspiring as hers. It is not everyday that you hear about a girl winning a 5km marathon out of nowhere, considering the fact that she never ran a marathon before that. If you would allow me - forget marathon, she had not run in any race apart from her day to day races with the bulls and cows on the rural fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aakansha lives a few miles away from the buzzing city of Kanpur in a small village named Ishwariganj with her mother, her uncle’s house overlooking hers. In a tragic turn of events, she lost her father to alcoholism 3 years ago. Like most households in the area, her family relies on supplies from the agri field for their livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unnat Bharat Abhiyan (UBA) and Techkriti, IIT Kanpur jointly organised a 5km marathon on 13th October 2018, which was a huge success. The marathon was open to all - schools, boys and girls up to the age of 20 were invited to register for the marathon for free. Among hundreds of other enthusiastic runners, Aakansha showed up in her day to day chappals, full of enthusiasm and the will to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her own words she did not expect to complete the marathon, let alone win it. But, she did - leaving about 200 other odd participants behind her. “I feel happy, and honored by it,” she said about the bicycle that she received as an award. The bicycle is helpful to her for her day to day commute, in ways more than one. She wishes to become a professional runner, and settle down as a police officer after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to stop right there for a moment and think about what she could achieve with proper training, and the right mentorship. Just think about it, this hugely talented girl comes out of nowhere and wins the race that defined her future goal, and the ambition to do something other than the ordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like you to think about other girls like her, may be in the millions that are just waiting for the right moment to spring to life. &lt;strong&gt;Can we do something as members of the society to nurture these talents?&lt;/strong&gt; I think yes, definitely. As a first step the schools can provide them free education under &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Right_of_Children_to_Free_and_Compulsory_Education_Act,_2009&quot;&gt;RTE&lt;/a&gt;. Schools, I believe should play a crucial role in identifying and nurturing young talents like her. The administration can set up infrastructures, facilities that would help them grow. The members of the community can be more supportive in terms of allowing girls to pursue and achieve their dreams. We definitely have thousands of talents like her, that are just waiting for that moment. The seeds that we sow in terms of support and opportunities for girls like her, would eventually result in the fruits that we are likely to reap in the upcoming times.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Debashish Reang</name></author><summary type="html">This post sums up a recent sitdown with one of the most energetic and ambitious person I met till date.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hacking into the TBSE Class X Exam Results 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/tbse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hacking into the TBSE Class X Exam Results 2018" /><published>2019-05-08T05:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-08T05:30:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/tbse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/tbse/">&lt;p&gt;This post summarizes our attempt to find tampering of marks in the final examination results published by the Tripura Board of Secondary Education (&lt;em&gt;called TBSE here on&lt;/em&gt;). We find that the system is deeply flawed and marks have been and are indeed tampered every year. This work is hugely inspired by that of &lt;a href=&quot;http://debarghyadas.com/writes/hacking-into-the-indian-education-system/&quot;&gt;Deedy’s&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Big shoutout to him!&lt;/strong&gt; We hope a few important changes would be enacted in the upcoming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before you read on:&lt;/strong&gt; Reang appeared in the Madhyamik Examination in the year 2015, and hence it is possible that personal biases crept in while writing the post. So, feel free to point them out if you notice any. There is also a high probability of us rambling, you have been &lt;strong&gt;warned!&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Examination:&lt;/strong&gt; Madhyamik exam is taken as the final exam during your Class X. In 2018, the exam was held from 6th March to 20th March, with the results published on 12th June. A total of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;45846&lt;/script&gt; students (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;22225&lt;/script&gt; Male &amp;amp; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;23621&lt;/script&gt; Female) took the exam, which is a 7.15% decrease from that in 2017. &lt;strong&gt;So far so good…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you wish, read up more on the summary of the exam and the statistics &lt;a href=&quot;http://tbse.in/new/Madhyamik2018Abstract.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The final results:&lt;/strong&gt; We scraped the final results using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/bs4/doc/&quot;&gt;BeautifulSoup&lt;/a&gt; from the result site. Scraping the results was easy since there was no extra information other than roll number was required. We just had to increment the roll numbers one by one. So much for privacy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chart.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Overall - no. of students vs marks: take note of the overshoot&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart is funny to us. You can clearly see that the marks are not &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_distribution&quot;&gt;normally distributed&lt;/a&gt;, as the marks of any standardised test should be. A Layman would probably straightaway tell you that there’s a peak somewehere around &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;250&lt;/script&gt;, and that number of students decreased towards the higher-mark spectrum. Now this is where things start to get interesting for us. Let us look at the district-wise breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dhalai.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in Dhalai district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/south.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in South district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/unokoti.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in Unokoti district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sepahi.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in Sepahijala district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/khowai.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in Khowai district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/west.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in West district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gomati.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in Gomati district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/north.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Marks distribution in North district&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that you’ve looked at the charts, you see that odd peak somewhere midway between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;200&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;300&lt;/script&gt; in  every graph. If you are disappointed with it, well you are not alone. Not a single district follows the ideal distribution of marks. The graphs are nowhere close to normal distribution by any means.
We tell you that the peak that you see is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt;. Yes! you read it right. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;844&lt;/script&gt; students got &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt; marks. Now you may ask, “What’s with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt;? Afterall it is a test score, so any number of students could have obtained it.” That’s where statistics disagree! &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt; coincidentally (really?) happens to be the pass mark (&lt;strong&gt;read&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;the mark which takes you to grade XI&lt;/em&gt; ). 7 subjects, you need &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;34&lt;/script&gt; each in subject to pass. so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;7 * 34 = 238&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/overall.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot;&gt;Combined graph&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few observations and thoughts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can clearly see that maximum number of students ended up getting &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt; marks. We are not claiming that it is not possible to obtaion &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt; marks, but a majority of those did not actually get that mark, rather they were given ‘grace-marks (how graceful!)’ and passed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the board does not care about transparency then who should the students who really worked hard turn to? We as a society should value hardwork, rather than passing students for the sake of fame and winning trophies for high-literacy and what not!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is often the case that the students who are just passed do not get admission anywhere else. Why not make them try another year rather than leaving them at the cross roads?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had the students been not given grace marks, say none got &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt; marks, then overall pass percentage would have dropped by ~&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;40&lt;/script&gt;%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary and concluding remarks:&lt;/strong&gt;
We saw the overall statistics of the exam result, then the district-wise break down of the marks distribution and how much they deviated from the ideal distribution. A whooping &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;844&lt;/script&gt; students got &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;238&lt;/script&gt; marks, the overall pass percentage would drop by ~&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;40&lt;/script&gt;% if the passing marks was say &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;240&lt;/script&gt; marks. We hope that this scenario improves over the coming years, and the concept of ‘grace-marks’ be scraped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future work:&lt;/strong&gt;
This year’s results would probably be published in the first/second week of June. To interested people at IITK: Do let me know if you are working on a similar thing, if you will, we can work together over the summer. &lt;strong&gt;Cheers!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments, reactions, and suggestions are welcome.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Debashish Reang</name></author><summary type="html">An attempt to make sense of tampering of marks in public examinations.</summary></entry></feed>