<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Debashish Reang</title>
    <description>Hi! I am Debashish Reang, a sophomore at the Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur. Deeply interested in Computer Science and Education, I aspire to get a PhD in Computational Biology and serve as a member of faculty.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Life Update: Few words on college life, food and travel</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a little bit of background about my college life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend, as I was sipping through my cup of coffee after an “intense” study-session, the thought of writing about my college life struck my mind. So here we are –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope I don’t bore you much and that you love what you read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always held this view that one must complete formal education unless except some extraordinary situation forces otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished my high school in April 2017 from NPS International School Guwahati. After that, I joined the Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur.
Well, many incidences happened between leaving high school and joining college, but I’ll keep that for another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to major in Electrical Engineering, mainly because my rank allowed me to do that and also among all the available options, EE at IITK seemed the best one for me.
I have to say that I do not at all regret my decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I also got selected for admission in IISc Bangaluru, but I did not join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are few images of Freshman Year that I posted on Facebook.&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/post.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fphoto.php%3Ffbid%3D1197756337036523%26set%3Da.110505532428281%26type%3D3&amp;amp;width=500&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;634&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/post.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fphoto.php%3Ffbid%3D1189728274505996%26set%3Da.541761669302663%26type%3D3&amp;amp;width=500&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;427&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a sophomore now. Life at IITK is going on well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 06:00:28 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/life%20update/2018/09/24/college.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/life%20update/2018/09/24/college.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome: Fall 2018.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello World!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing the readers to your writings with three vague words isn’t the best strategy to capture their attention but I shall try my best to do justice to your valuable time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that I’d write few daily articles, well quite the few, over the next two months on various issues that I may find or found interesting. I hope that we have meaningful discussions on my views on certain topics. The main motive behind writing these articles is to capture your attention and make you aware of the topics you may otherwise be unfamiliar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interesting picture to capture your interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/post.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fphoto.php%3Ffbid%3D1218912611587562%26set%3Da.344559545689544%26type%3D3&amp;amp;width=500&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;484&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I captured that, one morning during the course of bicycle trip to Bithoor. Beautiful isn’t it?
Kanpur as a city may not be green and beautiful but the mornings here and the people are amazing. Only, few times did I feel I was away from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back home, at this time of the year, I would most probably be out to ‘Puja’ shopping with mom. The weather during these months is really awesome, neither rainy nor cold or hot. You feel sleepy if you’re home or homesick if you’re away. Hey! you don’t get everything in life, simultaneously, do you? Afterall, the world isn’t a wish granting factory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But life is going great. I am grateful to the people in my life and this life. &lt;strong&gt;Welcome!&lt;/strong&gt; I hope you had a good reading time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 23:00:28 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/welcome/2018/09/23/welcome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/welcome/2018/09/23/welcome.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
